She's a good public speaker.
她很会公开演讲
I didn't know that.
我之前不知道
And maybe, you know,
也许，你知道
the last time I heard Mirka
我上次听米尔卡
speak publicly was probably
公开说话大概是
at our mixed doubles we
在我们打霍普曼杯
played at the Hopman Cup.
的混双时
24 years ago, maybe.
大概24年前
After one
打完一场
of our mixed doubles, we had
混双后，我们
to do an interview together.
要一起接受采访
Maybe this is the last time
也许那是她最后一次
she spoke publicly.
公开说话
So this is very well done.
所以这次说得非常好
I don't know
我不知道
if you've been, sorry,
你是不是，抱歉
secretly practicing,
偷偷练过
but this is very high level
但水平非常高
and a tough act to follow,
难以超越
but I'm so happy you did it.
但我很高兴你做到了
Thank you so much.
非常感谢
And also a shout out
还要致敬
to Fred Stolle who actually
弗雷德·斯托勒
did the interview,
他做了采访
also Hall of Famer.
也是名人堂成员
So that was obviously special.
所以那显然很特别
Let me just give a shout out
让我也向
to Mary as well.
玛丽致敬
That was amazing.
那太棒了
You crushed it.
你太厉害了
Incredible.
难以置信
So many stories, emotions,
这么多故事、情感
laughs.
欢笑
Congratulations
祝贺
on your whole team
你们整个团队
and your whole family
和你的所有家人
and everyone
以及每个人
who has supported you along
谁一直支持着你
the way. When I look,
一路走来。回首此刻，
I'm thrilled to have made
我很激动能
the journey here to the
来到这里，走进
International Tennis Hall
国际网球
of Fame.
名人堂。
You know,
你知道吗
this is a beautiful place
这是个美丽的地方
and I've really enjoyed every
我真的每一刻都很享受
minute so far.
到目前为止的每一分钟
I mean, of course I have.
我当然有
You've got grass courts here.
这里有草地球场
So my favorite.
所以是我的最爱
I was always going to have a
我一直都会在这里
wonderful time here.
度过美好时光
The museum is just incredible
博物馆真的太棒了
and I really encourage
我真的鼓励
everyone who comes here
每个来这里的人
to see it.
都去看看
There's
那里有
so much tennis history,
太多网球历史
rackets, trophies,
球拍、奖杯
iconic outfits from the greats
传奇球星的经典战袍
and they say they've got
他们还说有
more than, I was told,
超过，有人告诉我
25,000 artifacts
25,000件藏品
and now I guess I am one
现在我想我也
of them too.
是其中一员了
I mean, it's amazing to see yourself
我是说，看到自己
in a place like this to walk
置身这样的地方
through the Hall of Fame,
走过名人堂
to immerse myself
沉浸在这项
in the history of this sport.
运动的历史中
That means everything to me.
这对我意义重大
To read the stories
读到那些
of my greatest heroes
我最敬仰的英雄们的故事
and to realize,
并且意识到
I mean to truly realize
我是说真正意识到
for the first time
第一次
that I have a place here.
我在这里也有一席之地
This is one
这是
of the greatest honors
我人生中
of my life.
最大的荣耀之一
They call this the Hall
这里有个称呼
of Fame,
名人堂
but fame was never the goal.
但名气从来不是目标
My goal was to spend my
我的目标是用
life doing something I love,
一生做自己热爱的事
like what Mirka said,
正如米尔卡所说
with people who love it
和那些深爱它的人
as much as I do.
他们爱得和我一样深
And so many of those people
而且其中很多人
are here today.
今天都在这里
Family, friends
家人、朋友
who mean everything to me,
他们对我无比重要
fans who have traveled here
远道而来的球迷
to join us.
来和我们相聚
Some maybe over there.
有些也许在那边
I saw you before.
我之前看到你们了
Give me a shout out.
给我打个招呼吧
Help me out.
帮我撑撑场
They still show me
他们依然给我
so much support
非常大的支持
for so many years and wow,
这么多年了，哇
what a privilege
真是荣幸
to be with so many legends.
能和这么多传奇同台
Excuse me. So many legends
不好意思 这么多传奇
are all sitting right here.
都坐在眼前
Now
此时
that we're here together, I
既然大家齐聚于此
can tell you what it really took
我可以告诉你真正需要什么
to get into the Hall of Fame.
才能进入名人堂
Let's look at the numbers,
来看看这些数字
okay?
好吗
Not the obvious stats,
不是那些显而易见的统计数据
like the number of majors
比如大满贯数量
or number of weeks.
或者排名世界第一的周数
Number one, I'm talking
世界第一，我说的是
about the numbers
那些真正能说明问题的数据
that really paint a picture.
它们能描绘出全貌
Between 1998
从1998年
and when I first went
我第一次踏上
on the ATP tour
ATP巡回赛
and when I retired in 2022,
到2022年退役
I wore more than 5,000
我职业生涯戴过的头带
headbands in my career.
超过5000条
That's more than Borg and
甚至超过博格
McEnroe combined.
与麦肯罗两人的总和
That's right, Johnny Mack.
没错，强尼·麦克
I mean, I think it's more.
我是说，我觉得不止如此
For some reason,
不知为何
the tour doesn't keep count
巡回赛不统计
of the headbands,
发带的数量
but of course I do.
但我当然自己数
If you think that's impressive,
如果你觉得那很厉害
I wore probably
我大概穿了
over 7,000 pairs of socks.
七千多双袜子
That's probably twice as many
那可能是两倍
as most of my opponents
比我大多数对手
because I doubled them up.
因为我穿两双
And at one time
还有一次
in my first -round match
在我的首轮比赛中
at Wimbledon,
在温布尔登
I was so nervous I even wore
我紧张得甚至穿了
three pairs of socks.
三双袜子
I realized after the match.
赛后我才发现
Also, my stringers strung
此外，我的穿线师们穿了
about 10,000 rackets
大约10,000把球拍
over 25 years,
历时25年
and that's two tight stringers,
这要归功于两位出色的穿线师
Ron and Nate,
罗恩和内特
thank you guys.
谢谢你们
But really, there's no way
但说真的，根本无法
to measure what it means
衡量来到这里
to be here.
对我意味着什么
It's hard to put it into words,
很难用语言表达
but I'll try.
但我试试
I've had the privilege
我很荣幸
of walking onto the grass
走上草地球场
of Centre Court
在中央球场
at Wimbledon, of course,
当然是在温布尔登
looking up at Mirka
抬头看着米尔卡
and our four kids, Myla,
和我们的四个孩子，米拉
Charlene, Leo, and Lenny,
夏琳、利奥和莱尼
seeing my parents, Robbie
看到我的父母，罗比
and Lynette, seeing my team
还有莱内特，看到我的团队
and looking across the net
再看向球网对面
and seeing some
看到一些
of the greatest competitors
最伟大的竞争者
who have ever played
他们曾驰骋于
the game.
网坛
I've had the privilege
我有这样的荣幸
of stepping onto the red clay
踏上红土球场
of Roland Garros
来到罗兰·加洛斯
for the French Open,
征战法国网球公开赛
the privilege of looking up
也有幸抬头仰望
at thousands of tennis fans
万千网球迷
in Melbourne Park.
在墨尔本公园
For the Australian Open,
澳大利亚网球公开赛
of course, that is the US Open
当然还有美国网球公开赛
at Flushing Meadows
在法拉盛草原
and Tuesday night was epic.
周二晚上太精彩了
Thank you guys
谢谢你们
for playing part in it.
参与其中
Thank you, Andy.
谢谢你，安迪
And then, of course,
然后当然
the ATP Finals in Houston,
休斯顿的ATP年终总决赛
Shanghai and London.
上海和伦敦
Images like
像这样的画面
these are imprinted
都深深印在脑海里
in my mind
我的脑海里
and they're all part
它们都是
of me today.
如今我的一部分
Yet, when I close my eyes
然而，当我闭上眼睛
and think and dream
思考和梦想
of the game I love,
我热爱的比赛时
here's what I see.
我看到了这些
I just need a sip for this one.
我得喝一口
One second.
等一下
All right.
好了
I'm in Basel, Switzerland.
我在瑞士巴塞尔
I'm 13 years old
我13岁
and it's the Swiss indoors.
那是瑞士室内赛
I'm not competing. I'm a ball
我没有参赛
boy.
我是球童
I'm standing
我只是站着
against the back wall,
背靠着后墙
hands behind me,
双手放在身后
eyes on the ball.
眼睛盯着球
I'll never forget how
我永远不会忘记
the game looked from there
从那里看比赛的样子
and how it felt.
和那种感觉
The thrill of standing
站得那么近的兴奋感
so close to the players,
离球员那么近
feeding them the ball,
给他们喂球
handing them the towel,
给他们递毛巾
seeing them sweat,
看他们流汗
watching them fight it out,
看他们拼搏
figure it out, the adversity,
想办法应对逆境
the intensity.
那种强度
I remember the next morning
我记得第二天早上
my legs were gone.
我的腿完全没力气了
Standing all day is a lot
站一整天真的很
of work.
累
So I really want
所以我真的很想
to thank every ball kid
感谢每一位球童
who ever stood
他们曾经站着
through my matches, or all
看完我的比赛
our matches for that matter,
我们的比赛也是
for hours on end.
一打就是好几个小时
I see you.
我看到你们
I thank you.
我感谢你们
I was you.
我也曾是你们
By the time I was 13,
到我13岁的时候
I had been in love with tennis
我已经爱上网球
for a decade already.
整整十年了
My parents tell me I picked
我父母说我三岁
up a racket when I was three.
就拿起了球拍
My dad's wooden racket.
是我爸爸的木拍
That's right.
没错
I grew up
我从小
with the wooden rackets.
用的是木拍子
And white tennis balls.
还有白色网球
That's how old I am.
说明我有多老
And that racket was so heavy.
那个拍子特别重
I used to play double -handed
我以前正手双手握拍
forehand and double -handed
反手也是
backhand.
双手握拍
Who knew I was going
谁知道后来
to become
我会变成
a single -handed player?
单手选手
And are there any
现在还有
one -handers left
单手球员吗
in the game today
如今的网坛
or here tonight?
或者今晚在场的？
All right.
好的。
We're the proud few guys.
我们是骄傲的少数人。
Thank you.
谢谢。
And Switzerland was honestly
瑞士老实说
an amazing place to grow up.
是个很棒的成长之地
My parents gave
我父母给了
my sister Diana and me
我和我姐戴安娜
a wonderful childhood.
一个美好的童年
I had a lot of support
我有很多支持
to do what I love to do.
去做我热爱的事
And as a kid,
小时候
that meant hitting balls
那意味着打球
against bedroom cupboards,
对着卧室的柜子击球
my grandparents' garage
祖父母的车库
door, and all the walls
门，还有所有的墙
at the tennis clubs.
在网球俱乐部
It meant playing football
也意味着踢足球
with my friends.
和朋友们
I was Maradona or Zidane.
我是马拉多纳或齐达内
I'm playing basketball.
打篮球时
I was Jordan or Shaq,
我是乔丹或奥尼尔
of course.
当然
We had the Walkman
我们还有随身听
on while we rode
在我们滑滑板
our skateboards and bikes.
和骑自行车的时候
And after all, it was the 80s
而且毕竟是80年代
and the 90s.
和90年代
We played table tennis.
我们打乒乓球
We played badminton
我们打羽毛球
over the fence
隔着篱笆
with our neighbor.
跟邻居一起
And for a minute,
有一阵子
I even had a cricket bat.
我甚至有板球拍
But tennis, for me,
但网球对我来说
was the main event.
才是重头戏
Tennis became the fabric
网球成了我生活的底色
of my life.
贯穿我的一生
Mom had a full -time job,
妈妈有份全职工作
but she found time
但她还是挤出时间
to work the badge office
在赛事证件处工作
for the Swiss indoors
为瑞士室内赛工作
and probably
可能还
did some badges
也许你们当年的证件
for you guys.
也出自她手
So she was also the one
所以也是她
who organized my lesson
帮我安排了课程
to sign me up for matches
给我报名比赛
and supported my coaches.
还支持我的教练
Mom made it happen.
妈妈促成了这一切
Thank you, Mom.
谢谢你，妈妈
And she played tennis herself
她自己也在我们当地俱乐部
at our local club.
打过网球
I've been told
我听说
my dad played too.
我爸爸也打网球
Just kidding.
开个玩笑
He can take a joke.
他开得起玩笑
He likes to joke around.
他喜欢开玩笑
Thanks to both my mom
谢谢我的妈妈
and dad for all the time spent
和爸爸花的所有时间
on the court with me.
在球场上陪我
What I remember
我印象最深的是
was my dad's total ban
我爸完全禁止
on moon balls.
打月亮球
When I played him, he had
我跟他打的时候
the old continental grip.
他用的是老式大陆式握拍
That made me
这让我
for sure a more aggressive
无疑让我变得更敢进攻
tennis player.
网球选手
Thanks, Dad, Robbie Federer,
谢谢爸爸，罗比·费德勒
the real RF.
真正的 RF
On our street next
就在我们街上
to the community gardens,
挨着社区花园
my friends
我的朋友们
and I would use chalk to draw
我会用粉笔画
a court and stretch out a net
一个球场 拉一张网
and play mini tennis
打迷你网球
with a softball.
用的是软球
We played deep
我们一直打到
into the summer nights
夏夜很深
or longer.
甚至更晚
And that word, play,
而玩这个词
says a lot.
说明了很多
We play tennis.
我们打网球
We're tennis players.
我们是网球选手
That, for me,
对我来说
is what it's about, the sense
关键就是
of play.
玩的感觉
Yes, this sport takes work
是的 这项运动需要努力
and practice, but the sense
和练习 但玩的感觉
of play always carried me
一直支撑着我
through.
走下去
And when the work
当努力
and play blend together,
和玩乐融为一体
that's the best feeling of all.
那是最棒的感觉
Which is why I turned pro.
这也是我转职业的原因
I didn't see myself
我没把自己看作
as a professional athlete.
职业运动员
I was a tennis player,
我是网球选手
plain and simple.
说白了
And I was part
我是这个圈子里
of a community
的一份子
of tennis players
网球运动员
and tennis people.
和网球圈的人
It was on me whether I won
赢不赢都取决于我自己
or I lost.
还是输球
I was the guy
我就是那个
on court serving, slicing,
在场上发球、切削、
smashing, winning, losing.
扣杀、赢球、输球的人
I loved that. But I also learned
我喜欢那样。但我也学到了
that tennis is never
网球从来不是
about the players alone.
不只是球员本身
It's a whole ecosystem.
这是一个完整的生态
It's moms
有像我父母那样的妈妈
and dads like mine taking
和爸爸
their kids to matches,
带孩子去看比赛
cheering them on.
给他们加油
It's coaches
有教练
who teach children how
教孩子们如何
to win and how
去赢
to bounce back
以及如何重新振作
when they lose.
在输球后
It's people
还有人们
who sweep the courts
还有打扫球场的人们
or pick up the balls,
或者捡球
it's young players like me
是像我这样的年轻球员
who get a chance
有机会
to be a ball kid.
当球童
And also, by the way,
还有顺便说一下
it's the linespeople.
还有司线员
That's right. When I played
没错 我打球时
tennis, like with all of us here,
就像我们在场所有人一样
we used
我们以前
to have the linespeople,
都有司线员
remember?
记得吗
And tennis is an ecosystem
网球是一个生态系统
of all those people
所有这些人
and, of course, the fans.
当然还有球迷们
Just making sure
只是想确认
we're still now
我们现在依然
with the night coming,
随着夜晚来临
we're still awake.
我们还醒着
And the long speech,
还有这长长的致辞
I hope it's not too long.
希望不算太长
And I was a tennis fan
在成为球员之前
before I was a player
我就是网球迷
and I'm still a fan
现在仍然是球迷
and will always be.
而且永远都是
And if you want
如果你们想要
to know how I played,
想知道我打得怎么样
you can find the answer here
你可以在这里找到答案
at the Hall of Fame
就在名人堂
or on YouTube.
或者上 YouTube
But if you want
但如果你想
to know why I played,
知道我为什么打球
the answer is found
答案要去
in Switzerland,
瑞士寻找
on Waterhouse Street
就在瓦瑟豪斯街
and at the Old Boys Club
在老男孩俱乐部
in Basel and at Swiss Tennis
在巴塞尔和瑞士网球协会
in Écublan and Biel.
在埃居布朗和比尔
Why is a question I've asked
‘为什么’这个问题
a lot?
我问过很多次
Pierre Paganini,
皮埃尔·帕格尼尼，
my fitness trainer
我的体能教练
and mentor, will tell you
兼导师，会告诉你
that when I was at Écublan,
我在埃居布朗的时候，
I had a lot of questions.
问过很多问题。
I mean, a lot.
我是说，真的很多。
I nearly killed Pierre
我差点用好奇心
with my curiosity.
把皮埃尔逼疯。
Pierre,
皮埃尔，
I'm thankful you survived
感谢你在我
my time at Écublan.
埃居布朗期间活了下来
Your invaluable guidance
你宝贵的指导
and long -term
和长期的规划
strategy helped me
帮助了我
for my whole career.
贯穿我整个职业生涯
That ball kid had a lot
那个当过球童的孩子还有很多
to learn, skills and shots,
要学，技巧和击球
stamina and strategy.
体能和策略
Also, that kid
还有，那个孩子
had to learn not to throw
必须学会别老扔
his racket so much.
他的球拍
Ideally, not at all.
最好一次都别扔
Not to let his emotions get
别让情绪
the best of him to find
占据上风，还要找到
the balance between fire
在火与冰之间
and ice.
找到平衡
And thankfully, I had a lot
很幸运，我有
of incredible role models.
很多了不起的榜样
Here's my personal Hall
下面是我的个人
of Fame.
名人堂
Pierre's in there.
皮埃尔也在里面
So are all my coaches.
我的教练们也是
I'm talking about the
我说的是
phenomenal Peter Carter,
非凡的彼得·卡特
super-cool Peter Lundgren,
超酷的彼得·伦德格伦
two men who unfortunately
两位不幸的男士
are no longer with us,
已不在我们身边
who not only helped my game
他们不只提升了我的球技
but helped me grow up fast
也让我在旅途中
on the road.
迅速成长
I love you guys. Thank you.
我爱你们 谢谢
Also, legendary coaches
还有传奇的教练们
Jose Higueras, Paul Annacone
何塞·伊格拉斯、保罗·安纳孔
and Tony Roach.
还有托尼·罗奇
I love my time with them
我很喜欢和他们在一起的时光
and I learned
我学到了很多
so much from their stories
从他们的故事
and expertise.
和经验里
And I was lucky
我很幸运
to have my childhood hero,
能有我儿时的偶像
Stefan Edberg.
斯特凡·埃德伯格
That's not a first, am I?
这可不是第一次了，对吧
God, those are happy tears.
天哪，这是幸福的眼泪
I had you in my corner,
有你在我的团队里
who provided huge
你给了我巨大鼓舞
personal inspiration
那是个人层面的激励
for the everyday grind
支撑着我度过
on the tour.
巡回赛上日复一日的磨砺
And my amazing friend Reto
还有挚友雷托·施陶布利
Staubli, who helped me
他曾帮助我
during an amazing stretch
走过一段非凡时期
while balancing
同时兼顾
his banking life with coaching
银行工作与执教
and Ivan Ljubicic, who had a
还有伊万·柳比契奇，他
tremendous impact working
与我合作的最后六年里
with me for the last six years
产生了巨大影响
in the twilight of my career.
那是我职业生涯的尾声
It's getting tough now.
现在越来越难了
I thought it was going
我以为这场
to be easy, this one.
会很轻松
And Severin Lutti,
还有塞弗林·吕蒂
my longest tenured coach.
我任期最长的教练
18 long years together.
一起走过18个漫长的年头
Severin's role in my life
塞弗林在我人生中的分量
and my career is even bigger
和职业生涯里的分量更大
than that number.
比那个数字还大
He kept me motivated
他一直激励着我
when I needed motivating
在我需要动力的时候
and he protected me
而且他也保护着我
when I needed protecting.
在我需要保护时
Yeah, we'll get through this.
我们会挺过去
Promise.
我保证
Until the sun rises, guys.
直到太阳升起，伙计们
Oh, God.
哦，天哪
Yo, your insights
你的见解
were super crucial.
至关重要
Thank you to all my success.
感谢所有成就我的人
And together we had a blast.
我们一起度过了美好时光
Physios and my doctor,
理疗师和我的医生
Roland, are in my hall
罗兰也在我心中
of fame too.
的名人堂里
I thought I was doing
刚才有那么一秒
so well for a second.
我觉得自己表现不错
Oh, man.
哦天哪
Okay.
好吧
Where are we?
说到哪了
No, so I needed a lot
不，我需要很多
of the help from Roland,
来自罗兰的帮助
Danny, Steph,
丹尼、斯蒂芬、
Gary, Pavel, helped
加里、帕维尔，帮我
a young body get strong and
让年轻的身体变强，
an old body keep working.
让年老的身体还能运转。
Thanks for all the good times
谢谢你们带来的美好时光
and the late hours, guys.
和那些深夜，伙计们。
One at a time.
一次一个
Right?
对吧
Almost there. Thank you,
快到了，谢谢
Martina.
玛蒂娜
Yes, any help at this point,
是的，现在任何帮助都行
but this is a good one.
不过这个办法不错
Thank you.
谢谢
Tony is in my hall of fame
托尼也在我的名人堂里
and every athlete has people
每个运动员身边都有人
who help shape a career.
帮他们塑造职业生涯
Tony's done even more than
而托尼做的远不止
that.
这些
For over 20 years,
二十多年来
he's helped me think bigger
他帮我想得更远
and bolder
也更大胆
about the world beyond
去看巡回赛之外
the tour.
更大的世界
We've built things together
我们一起做了些事
that make me incredibly
令我无比
proud.
骄傲
New ventures,
新的冒险
new partnerships.
新的合作
And along the way,
一路走来
the agent became a friend
经纪人成了朋友
and the friend became family.
朋友成了家人
That includes
这包括
your wonderful Mary Jo,
还有你了不起的玛丽·乔
who plays a special role.
她也扮演着特殊角色
Tony
托尼
and I have had the chance
和我有机会
to develop
发展出
the greatest relationship
最棒的关系
with some
与一些
of the greatest global brands.
全球顶级品牌
And I just want
我只想
to thank my sponsors
感谢我的赞助商
and premium partners
和高级合作伙伴
for believing in me
相信我
from the early days to today
从最初直到今天
and for being incredible
也感谢你们如此出色
creative partners
成为我的创意伙伴
who have become friends
后来又成为朋友
over the years, making life
让这些年的巡回生活
on tour even much more fun.
更有趣了
Thank you, guys.
谢谢你们
And
还有
that includes people like Roy,
也包括罗伊这样的人
who along
他与团队并肩
with other teammates
也和其他队友一起
have supported me
始终支持着我
with a million things
处理过无数事务
over the years,
这么多年来
plus the many tournament
还有众多赛事
directors and everybody
总监和每个人
who supports them.
支持他们的人
The ecosystem is incredible.
这个生态太了不起了
Thank you, guys.
谢谢大家
All right.
好了
My hall of fame also includes
我的名人堂也有
some official hall of famers,
一些正式入选的名人堂成员
like Boris Becker,
像鲍里斯·贝克尔
Stefan Edberg.
斯特凡·埃德伯格
I remember sitting
我记得坐在那里
on the floor
在家里的地板上
in our living room,
在我们的客厅里
watching those guys play
看着他们
in the Wimbledon finals again
一次又一次
and again and again.
征战温网决赛
And, of course,
当然
there was Pete Sampras,
有皮特·桑普拉斯
the best serve ever.
史上最好的发球
What a privilege
多么荣幸
to have shared a court.
能在同一片球场交手
Your turn now.
该你了
Okay.
好
And two—not one, but two—
还有两位，不是一位
Martinas.
玛蒂娜
First, Martina Hingis,
首先是玛蒂娜·辛吉斯
Swiss like me.
瑞士人，跟我一样
World number one by the age
16岁就排名世界第一
of 16, unlike me.
这我可比不上
And Martina Navratilova.
还有玛蒂娜·纳芙拉蒂洛娃
You know
你知道
her for winning 59 majors.
她拿过59座大满贯冠军
But in our house,
但在我们家里
she's famous
她最有名的是
for inspiring Mirka
激励了米尔卡
to play tennis.
开始打网球
I need tissues
我需要纸巾
and sunglasses.
和墨镜
I need everything
我需要一切
to protect me right now.
来保护自己
Oh, man.
天哪
Okay.
好吧
Yeah. Okay.
是的。好的。
Oh, my God. Now we're going
天哪。现在我们要
into the Mirka bit.
进入米尔卡的部分了。
This is such...
这真是……
This is such a mess.
这真是一团糟。
So Martina inspired Mirka,
所以是玛蒂娜激励了米尔卡，
and Mirka inspires me every
米尔卡每天都激励我
day.
日日如此
As you know,
如你所知
Mirka is my wife, duh,
米尔卡是我妻子啦
which is the greatest
这实在太过轻描淡写
understatement I can make.
也是我最保守的表达
Because she's also
因为她也
been my coach,
一直当我的教练
my hitting partner
我的练球搭档
before matches, and sorry,
赛前也是，抱歉
man, my reality check,
还是那个让我认清现实的人
also my stylist.
还是我的造型师
I definitely needed one
我当时确实需要一个
at the time.
在那会儿
Maybe I don't know now.
也许现在还是，我也不知道
But Mirka is the person
但米尔卡是那个
who showed me how
让我懂得怎么
to get more focused
对网球更专注
about tennis and take joy
也能尽情享受
in everything else.
网球之外的一切
A wonderful mother
她也是一位好母亲
to our four kids who make
我们的四个孩子
the impossible happen
把不可能变成现实
in all our lives.
在我们所有人的生活里
She and I grab
她和我抓住
each other's hands,
彼此的手
and we run through walls.
然后我们一起冲破墙壁
Thank you.
谢谢
Oh, God.
哦，天哪
So she's all of these things,
所以她集合了所有这些
and that's my Hall of Fame.
这就是我的名人堂
Although the list of legends
不过，为我铺路的传奇
who paved the way is even longer
名单其实还要长得多
than that: Laver, Emerson,
拉沃尔、埃默森
Rosewall, Borg, McEnroe,
罗斯沃尔、博格、麦肯罗
Marc Rosset, who was like
马克·罗塞特，他就像
a brother to me on the tour
巡回赛上的兄弟
who won the Olympics
他为瑞士赢得奥运冠军
for Switzerland 16 years
早在16年前
before my man Stan
后来我的兄弟斯坦
and I had the honor
和我也有幸
to do the same.
做到同样的事
I learned from all of them,
我从他们所有人身上学习
and eventually I
最终我
had to figure out
必须搞清楚
my own identity.
我自己的身份。
Okay.
好的。
It feels like more downhill
现在应该轻松多了
now.
接下来
Which evolved over time,
我的身份也随时间演变
and this meant one thing
它曾有一种样子
in 1998 when I became the
那是在1998年
Junior World Number One.
我成为青少年世界第一时
That version
那个版本的我
of me had bleach blonde hair,
染了金色头发
which has caused me a lot
给我带来了很多
of embarrassment to this day.
至今都感到尴尬
It meant something different
意义不一样
in 2022 when I played
2022年我打
my last match in London.
在伦敦的最后一场时
That version
那个版本的我
of me had 4,040 total sets
已经让这双膝盖承受了4,040盘
on his knees,
比赛的重压
and that's just singles matches.
而且那还只是单打比赛
It doesn't include
它不包括
the doubles, qualies,
双打、资格赛
Challengers, Futures, satellites,
挑战赛、希望赛、卫星赛
practice sets, same knees.
训练盘——还是这双膝盖
Still got them, by the way,
顺带一提，膝盖还好着呢
and if I fall, please catch me,
如果我跌倒 请接住我
okay?
好吗
But at every stage
但在我职业生涯的每个阶段
of my career, I tried above all
我首先努力
to stay true to myself,
忠于自己
and I tried to show my love
并努力展现我的爱
for the game
对这项运动
because it really mattered
因为它对我真的很重要
to me, and I also wanted it
而且我也希望它
to matter to you.
对你也重要
To be worthy
配得上
of your attention,
你的关注
worthy of your attendance,
配得上你的到场
because people don't
因为大家并不是
have to come watch us play.
非得来看我们打球
They come to be entertained,
他们来是为了娱乐
inspired, excited.
被激励，感到兴奋
They could always decide
他们随时可以决定
to go somewhere else,
去别的地方
but they chose tennis,
但他们选择了网球
they chose us.
他们选择了我们
Everywhere I played,
我所到之处
you made me feel like I
你们让我感觉好像
had home court advantage.
我拥有主场优势
I've always wanted people
我一直希望人们
to see how great it feels
看看这感觉有多棒
to play this game,
打网球这件事
how great it feels
感觉有多棒
to have a ball hit hard at you,
球狠狠朝你飞来
the way it spins,
它旋转的方式
the sound it makes,
它发出的声音
the way it bounces,
它的弹跳方式
how geometry shifts
几何关系如何变化
as the ball moves
当球移动
towards you and how
向你而来，以及
the court itself opens
球场本身打开
or shrinks.
或缩小
Tennis is a complex
网球很复杂
and beautiful thing.
也是件美丽的事
It is spectacular to watch.
看起来太壮观了
You're the fan, you see it all.
你是球迷 全都看在眼里
You live it with us every point.
每一分你都和我们一起经历
As you know, there's a lot
你知道 网球里有
of pressure in tennis,
很大压力
a volcano of pressure,
像火山一样的压力
volcano of emotions,
像火山一样喷涌的情绪
and when the match
而比赛
was over, win or lose,
结束的时候 不管输赢
you probably saw what I
你可能看到了我
was feeling inside.
内心的感受
What can I say?
我还能说什么
Tennis meant the world
网球对我来说意味着全世界
to me, not just playing,
不只是打球
not just winning,
不只是赢球
but creating something new.
而是创造新的东西
It's a mentality I have.
这是我的一种心态
I used to play serve and volley.
我以前打发球上网
I had a transition game.
我也打过衔接进攻
I played way behind
有时站在远离
the baseline sometimes
底线的位置
or on top of the baseline,
或压在底线上
and I would even try
我甚至会尝试
to sneak up on my opponents
偷偷逼近对手
on my return, and some call it
就在接发时，这后来被叫作
the SABR today.
如今被称作SABR
This is what was important
这些是
to me on the court,
球场上对我重要的事
but so much
但还有许多
of what was really important
真正重要的事情
happened off the court.
都发生在球场之外
The camaraderie
比如那份情谊
in the locker room,
发生在更衣室里
guys, playing cards
伙计们打牌
with the team until
和团队一起，一直待到
the last second
最后一秒
before matches,
赛前
laughing with everyone, even
和大家一起笑，甚至
my opponents sometimes.
有时和对手也笑
So many of us
我们很多人都
have become friends through
通过共同的经历
our shared experiences
成为了朋友
and battles on the court
还有球场上的较量
that connect us through life.
把我们的一生相连
Those are some
那些是
of the best memories
我在巡回赛上
of playing on tour.
最美好的回忆之一
But there's another kind
但还有另一种
of play.
玩乐
The kind that happens
那是另一种快乐
with friends,
和朋友一起时
and especially family.
尤其和家人在一起
Family again, okay.
还是家人
With Mirka,
和米尔卡一起
we started out doing things
我们最初会一起做些事
like playing video games
就像打游戏
and doing clubbing.
还有泡夜店
Oh, yeah.
哦，是啊
And having late dinners
还有和朋友一起
with friends.
吃很晚的晚饭
Then it shifted
后来这些变成了
into changing diapers
换尿布
and staying in hotels
还有入住酒店
with elevators, big enough
那些电梯得足够大
for double strollers,
能放下双人婴儿车
and goodnight stories
还有睡前故事
with the kids.
跟孩子们一起
Myla, Charlene, Leo, and Lenny,
米拉、夏琳、利奥和莱尼
you definitely changed
你们确实改变了
our lives.
我们的生活
And you inspired us,
你们激励了我们
make us...
让我们……
You inspire and make us
你们激励着我们 让我们
happy every day.
每天都开心
Thank you, guys.
谢谢你们
Our family
我们一家人
has traveled together across
一起走遍了
the world.
全世界
Yep, we always return
是的，我们总会回到
to our home country,
我们的祖国
Switzerland.
瑞士
It has always
一直以来
been an immense honor
都是莫大的荣幸
to represent the flag
能代表
of Switzerland.
瑞士
And tonight, as my...
而今夜，作为我的...
Don't have to laugh about it.
不用非得笑
Tonight, as my name enters
今晚，当我的名字进入
the Hall of Fame, I'm proud
名人堂，我很自豪
that Switzerland comes
瑞士与我
with me.
同行
It's
这
been an incredible journey.
是一段不可思议的旅程
For me,
对我而言
the International Tennis Hall
国际网球名人堂
of Fame provides
提供了一个
a great opportunity
绝佳的机会
to look back,
回顾过去
but also to look ahead.
同时也展望未来
As you can tell,
你们都看得出来
I'm still writing my love letter
我仍在续写
to tennis.
给网球的情书
My time as a player is done,
作为球员我已退役
but tennis will always stand
但网球永远会
at the intersection of
在我最珍视的一切
everything I care most about.
交汇的那个地方
My family, our friendships,
家人、友情
the past 40 years,
过去四十年
the future we're building,
我们构筑的未来
tennis for me is responsible
网球对我而言
for it all.
是这一切的缘由
So this is not a goodbye.
所以这不是告别
But before I close,
但在结束之前
I want to share my hopes
我想分享我对这项运动
for this sport.
的期望
The International Tennis Hall
国际网球名人堂
of Fame shows the evolution
展现了网球的演变
of tennis, and I'm honored
我很荣幸
to be part of that.
能成为其中一部分
And I'm incredibly lucky
我无比幸运
to have bridged
能够连接
the generations from Pete
从皮特和安德烈这样的巨星
and Andre the superstars
到我自己时代
to champions in my own age,
的冠军们
like Roddick, Hewitt,
像罗迪克、休伊特
Safin and Ferrero.
萨芬和费雷罗
To the epic rivalries I have
以及我与下一代
with the next generation,
之间的史诗对决
Andy, Novak and Rafa,
安迪、诺瓦克和拉法
we all leave
我们终究都会离开
the court eventually,
赛场
but the sport keeps evolving.
但这项运动一直在进化
And as the pace of
随着职业网球的节奏
professional tennis speeds up
不断加快
as the sport becomes
随着这项运动
even more global,
变得更加全球化
I so hope it will keep some
我真心希望保留一些
of that amateur spirit keep
那份业余精神，也保留
the camaraderie
那种情谊
among the players.
在球员当中
I hope the players
我希望球员们
will stay young at heart
永远保持年轻的心
and stay true
并忠于
to their authentic selves.
忠于真实的自己
And always remember,
永远记住
never stop asking questions
不要停止提问
or taking risks.
或冒险
Do things with the game
去创造这项运动中
we've never seen before.
我们从未见过的事
Keep pushing
继续推动
this sport we love
这项我们热爱的运动
to the next level.
迈向新的高度
And keep getting better,
而且不断进步
better and better.
越来越好
And I hope, yeah,
我也希望如此
let's give it a round.
让我们为他们鼓掌
Come
来吧
on for the future generation,
为了下一代
guys.
鼓掌吧
Let's do it.
一起行动吧
And I hope you
我希望你们
will find other ways
会找到其他方式
to give something back
去回馈
to share your passion.
分享你的热情
There are a thousand ways
有成千上万种方式
to do that.
可以做到这一点
For me it
对我来说
was creating a foundation
就是创立一个基金会
which does work
从事相关工作
in southern Africa,
在非洲南部
where mom
妈妈来自那里
is from, and Switzerland
还有瑞士
where my dad is from.
我爸爸的家乡
My team and I also created
我的团队和我还创办了
the Laver Cup to honor
拉沃尔杯，以致敬
the legend of all generations.
历代传奇
Thank you.
谢谢
And to everyone here,
对在座每个人
I hope you will be a bridge
希望你们架起桥梁
between the tennis
连接两种网球
that happens at the level
一边是职业网球
of the ATP, WTA,
ATP、WTA
ITF and all the slams
ITF和所有大满贯
and the tennis that's played
另一边是日常网球
as the sun goes down on a
日落时分仍在继续
quiet street like Wasserhaus
瓦瑟豪斯那样安静的街道上
where I grew up.
那是我长大的地方
Tennis that's played
还有遍布各地的网球
everywhere from Switzerland
从瑞士到南非
to South Africa, Slovakia,
斯洛伐克
India and Brazil, anywhere
印度和巴西，任何地方
that kids draw courts
孩子们用粉笔在街上
in the streets with chalk like I
画球场，就像我
did.
以前那样
Where they hit against walls
他们对着墙击球
with borrowed rackets
用借来的球拍
where parents get the kids
父母带孩子们
to practice,
去练球
where coaches work
教练们辛勤工作
and fans show up
球迷们来到现场
in the blazing sun
无论烈日
or the bitter cold.
还是严寒
Where the ball kids
球童们
have their knee
单膝跪下
on the ground and are ready
已经蓄势待发
to move.
随时起身跑动
I will always see the sport
我总会透过他们的眼睛
through their eyes.
看待这项运动
So this boy
所以这个巴塞尔的男孩
from Basel thanks you
感谢你们
for the incredible honor
感谢这无上的荣誉
and I thank you, all of you,
谢谢你们，谢谢在座各位
for sharing the journey
谢谢你们一路相伴
that brought us together.
是这段旅程让我们相聚